Guide to the Pittsburgh Mercantile Company Records, 1877-1950 AIS.1965.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Mercantile Company Records
1877-1950
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Mercantile Company
AIS.1965.06
21 Linear Feet
The Pittsburgh Mercantile Company operated in western Pennsylvania from the 1870s until the 1950s. The company was made up of clothing and dry goods stores, mainly patronized by steelworkers and coal miners. This collection contains various forms of ledgers including balance books, departmental ledgers, private ledgers, inventories, payroll, and share books.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Sy Silverman on February 17, 1965.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Mercantile Company Records, 1877-1950, AIS.1965.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions; however, users of this collection must make an appointment with the Archives Service Center before the collection can be serviced because of its current physical arrangment.
History
The Pittsburgh Mercantile Company operated in western Pennsylvania from the 1870s until the 1950s. The company was made up of clothing and dry goods stores, mainly patronized by steelworkers and coal miners. As in all mining and steel working towns, workers purchased all necessities from the company store. There were stores throughout western Pennsylvania in Pittsburgh, California, Fredericktown, Woodlawn, Vestaburg, and Denbo. The Pittsburgh Mercantile Company, the superstore of its day, offered household supplies, tools, and foods in addition to clothing. Although the stores were retail, the company made most of its profit from wholesale to companies and businesses. Some of the stores had service stations for the maintenance of automobiles.
Arrangement
The records are organized into eight series (additional notes are found at the series level):
Series I. Financial Ledgers, 1894-1949
Series II. Private Ledgers, 1875-1947
Series III. Tax Records, 1903-1931
Series IV. Shares, Vouchers, and Check Books, 1880-1936
Series V. Payroll, 1937-1941
Series VI. California, PA, Store Fire, January 3, 1946
Series VII. Inventory and Supply Ledgers, 1898-1937
Series VIII. Ledger of Contacts, 1904-1917
Scope and Content Notes
The records of the Pittsburgh Mercantile Company reflect the business activities of the company from 1877 to 1950. Most of the material is in the form of ledgers, which have been microfilmed. This collection contains many different forms of ledgers including balance books, departmental ledgers, private ledgers, inventories, payroll, and share books. Each type of ledger allows a glimpse into a function of the company.
Ledgers (Account books); Business and Industry; Stores, Retail -- Pennsylvania; Department stores -- Pennsylvania; General stores -- Pennsylvania; Pittsburgh Mercantile Company
- Financial Ledgers, 1894-1949; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains financial ledgers used by the company to manage assets as a whole and on a departmental basis. Balance books were used to balance the whole of the company's assets and expenses. Petty cash ledgers were used to keep track of accounts used for travel, emergencies, and jobs. These ledgers list names with dollar amounts including the financial balance of company and received and disbursed payments. Among the years listed, 1921 is missing. Financial ledgers account for the transactions between the Pitt Mercantile Co. and various businesses. The financial ledger mentions the Pennsylvania R.R. regarding shipments, cargo, destinations, and cost. The James Mfg. Co. ledger details the sale of wood alcohol, acetate of lime, hardwood charcoal.
  - Balance Book. American Iron Works Store, 1895-1901 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Balance Book. Pitt Mercantile, 1902-1904 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Balance Book, March 1905 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Balance Book. Recapitulation pages, 1911-1913 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Balance Book. All stores, 1930-1936 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Balance Book. Steel Industries Engineering Corporation, 1931-1936 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Financial Ledger. Kane, Pa., 1895-1906 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Financial Ledger. Consolidated Chemical Co., 1897-1906 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Financial Ledger. Kane & Elk R.R. Co., 1898-1901 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Financial Ledger. Freight Interchange Account, 1919-1927 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Financial Ledger. American Plate Galss, 1929-1930 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Financial Ledger. Pennsylvania R.R., 1898-1907 (Shelf 16/5/5)
  - Financial Ledger. Monthly statements, 1912 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Financial Ledger. Monthly statements, 1914-1916 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Financial Ledger. James Manufacturing Co., 1927-1932 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Financial Ledger. Steel Industries Engineering Co., 1930-1937 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Financial Ledger., 1900-1904 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1904-1912 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1915 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1924-1925 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1939-1940 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1941-1943 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1944-1945 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1947 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1947-1949 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Departmental ledgers, 1949 (Shelf 16/5/7-8)
  - Petty cash ledgers, 1914-1916 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Petty cash ledgers, 1914-1923 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Petty cash ledgers, 1919-1925 (Shelf 16/5/6)
  - Petty cash ledgers, 1923-1926 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Petty cash ledgers, 1925-1930 (Shelf 16/5/6)
  - Petty cash ledgers, 1926-1934 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Debits and Credits, 1894-1905 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Markups, 1924 (Shelf 16/5/4)
- Private Ledgers, 1875-1947; II.
  Series II consists of private ledgers, which were used primarily to manage the accounts of company executives and shareholders. Private journals are similar to private cash ledgers, but include statements as to why monies were displaced and offer a view of the company from upper management. The private ledger of the Blair Supply Co. contains a company charter.
  - Private Ledgers. American Iron Works Store, 1875 (Shelf 15/5/4-5)
  - Private Ledgers. American Iron Works Store, 1914-1922 (Shelf 16/5/4-5)
  - Private Ledgers. Blair Supply Co., 1904 (Shelf 16/5/4-5)
  - Private ledgers, 1904-1905 (Shelf 16/5/4-5)
  - Private ledgers, 1904-1905 (Shelf 16/5/4-5)
  - Private ledgers, 1910-1911 (Shelf 16/5/4-5)
  - Private ledgers, 1912-1913 (Shelf 16/5/4-5)
  - Private ledgers, 1923-1927 (Shelf 16/5/4-5)
  - Private cash ledgers, February 1907-March 1909 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private cash ledgers, 1905-1909 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private cash ledgers, 1909-1910 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private cash ledgers, 1911-1912 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1904-1913 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1904-1917 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1908-1912 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1917-1923 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1924-1930 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1930-1935 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1935-1940 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals, 1941-1945 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Private journals (bonuses from 1944), 1945-1947 (Shelf 16/5/1)
- Tax Records, 1903-1931; III.
  Series III contains the original taxes filed by the company for the years 1903 to 1931. The majority of these tax records are accompanied with correspondence from the U.S. Treasury Department due to an audit in the 1930s. The Pitt Mercantile Co. was audited due to unpaid stock balances and corporate loans from 1903 to 1931. Most of the material involves the company's appeal in 1931. Records relating to the Treasury Department audit contain correspondence on a hearing with Jones & Laughlin Steel Co. in 1923.
  - Treasury department audit, 1903-1923 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Treasury department audit. Assessment report, 1916-1920 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Treasury department audit, 1917 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Treasury department audit, 1924 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1918 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1919 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1920 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1920-1921 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1922-1923 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1923 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1924 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1925 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1926 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1927 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1928 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1929 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1930 (Shelf 16/5/1)
  - Tax returns, capital stock, corporate loans, 1931 (Shelf 16/5/1)
- Shares, Vouchers, and Check Books, 1880-1936; IV.
  Series IV contains certificates of stock or shares of the company, check registers, voucher books, account books, check stub books, and everything else that accompanied financial transactions. The certificate of stock book accounts for the companies stockholders from 1905 to 1929 (the year of the stock market crash). Incidentally, in 1929, the founder of the company essentially bought out the shareholders and held all the company shares.
  - Stocks and share accounts. Certificates of stock, 1905-1929 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Stocks and share accounts. Transfer book, 1905-1929 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Stocks and share accounts. Receipts of share holders, 1910 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Stocks and share accounts, 1912 (Shelf 16/5/4)
  - Voucher books, 1902-1906 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Voucher books, 1904-1930 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. American Iron Works Store, 1880-1889 (Shelf 16/5/5)
  - Check register. Pitt Mercantile, 1900-1904, 1901-1903 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. Pitt Mercantile. Account book, 1904-1907 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. West Branch National Bank, 1901-1904 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. Pittsburgh Store, 1904-1911 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. Consolidated Chemical Co., 1905-1906 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. James Mfg. Co., 1909, 1913-1916 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. Promissory notes, 1911-1917 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. Steel Industries Engineering Corp., 1930-1931, 1931-1936 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. Steel Industries Engineering Corp. Letter/copy book, 1937-1938 (Shelf 16/5/3)
  - Check register. Empty check book, undated (Shelf 16/5/3)
- Payroll, 1937-1941; V.
  Series V contains the payroll records of the company in the form ledger books. There are no social security numbers present. The departmental payroll list with the names of employees in military service lists payments made to employees, their mothers and fathers, spouses, and others.
  - Aliquippa and Pittsburgh Stores, 1937 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Aliquippa and Pittsburgh Stores. Private payroll book, 1938 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Department pay roll, 1937-1939 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Department pay roll, February 1939-January 1940 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Department pay roll, January-December 1940 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Department pay roll. Employees in military service, December 1940-December 1941 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Department pay roll, 1940-1941 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Department pay roll, January 1941-December 1941 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Department pay roll. Empty payroll sheets, undated (Shelf 16/5/2)
- California, Pa., Store Fire, January 3, 1946; VI.
  Series VI contains records relating to the company store fire in California, Pa., in 1946. Most of the records were brought together for insurance purposes after the incident in the Statement of Claim documents. The department inventories are arranged by department number and detail what was damaged and the financial value. All of the following items are in one volume.
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Inventory of items lost in fire, 1946 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Inventory, Daisytown store, dept.17, January 5, 1946
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Department 15 inventory lists, undated
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Department 16 inventory lists, undated
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Department 17 inventory lists, undated
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Department 18 inventory lists, undated
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Department 19 inventory lists, undated
  - Statement of claim from California, Pa. store. Department 21 inventory lists, undated
- Inventory and Supply Ledgers, 1898-1937; VII.
  Series VII contains the supply and inventory lists of the company stores and ledgers. The stock books are inventories of merchandise on-hand and supply lists of the Pitt Mercantile Co. The store journal is a brief account of daily activities at the Pittsburgh store during 1912-1913.
  - Stock books, 1904-1913 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Stock books. Pittsburgh store, 1905-1910 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Stock books, 1911-1913 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Stock books, 1912-1913 (Shelf 16/5/5)
  - Stock books, 1914-1923 (Shelf 16/5/5)
- Ledger of Contacts, 1904-1917; VIII.
  Series VIII consists of desk ledgers with alphabetical lists of names of companies, individuals, and businesses accounts.
  - Desk ledger, Blair Supply Co., 1904 (Shelf 16/5/2)
  - Ledger with names, 1916-1917 (Shelf 16/5/3)